Welcome to the TRT and hormone
optimization YouTube channel. And for
the first time with us is Dr. Farzam.
It's difficult to pronounce your first
name, I guess.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I go by Cash. So, yeah. Dr.
Cash. Some people call me. [laughter]
>> All right. So, uh maybe let's start by
uh introducing yourself.
>> Yeah. So, I'm a physician based in uh in
Canada. I'm uh about one hour west of uh
west of Toronto. Um, I grew up in
Canada. I do emergency medicine
full-time. I also do TRT and weight loss
medicine and hair loss medicine um in uh
out here in Kitchener, Ontario, just
outside of Toronto. And I've been a
focused practice in men's health for a
while now. And I also do econultations
for other physicians in Canada as well.
[snorts]
>> Awesome. All right. And then today we're
talking about male pattern baldness or
maybe baldness in general and on TRT.
>> Yeah. So I think the appro my approach
to hair loss and what I teach to others
as well is that um the first step is
making sure the diagnosis is correct. So
uh for some people they might start
losing hair and the automatic assumption
might be that it's definitely male
pattern baldness. And I think the my
first step is make sure the diagnosis is
correct. You can have hair loss from
fungal infections. You're going to have
hair loss from autoimmune illness. I
mean, a patient could have lupus. You
could have alopecia ariata. I mean,
there's all kinds of different
presentations, different systemic
illnesses where um you know, hair loss
could be a symptom. It doesn't mean
that's the it's only male pattern
baldness. So, and I tell that to
patients as well when they first come
in, it's make sure the diagnosis is
correct first. So once we've concluded
the diagnosis is male pattern baldness,
I think the next step afterwards is well
at least what I tell people is well it's
a personal choice on what you want to
do. Um if they have male pattern
baldness, well you want to decide you
want to you know does it matter for you?
Does it not matter? I mean that's kind
of what it comes down to. If it doesn't
matter great, no problem at all. I mean
it's a personal choice. um if it does
matter then I think you know from I
guess from our standpoint from the on
the you're sitting on the opposite end
of the patient then we can present some
options and so that my [clears throat] I
think first step is always making sure
patient understands why it's happening
and especially for our patients who are
on TRT it's a common question they ask
is about hair loss and whether it gets
worse whether it can cause hair loss and
I think the I [clears throat] like to
take a step back and tell patients hey
Listen, like um a lot of people or as I
should say, most men have some level of
predisposition to hair loss. As you get
older, hair will thin, hair will fall
out. That's natural, you know, timeline
[clears throat] events in life.
And so what I usually um will tell them
is um you know like uh once someone hits
puberty, once they make testosterone,
once that process of testosterone
conversion, DHT happens, um some people
are predisposed to male pattern
baldness, their hair can thin, their
hair can fall out. Now the reason why
that happens I mean so the hair
follicles
um can have essentially multiple levels
of predisposition to you know I don't
want to use the term toxicity but really
I mean the DHT that hydro testosterone
can be damaging to hair follicles um you
know at different extents depending on
the patient's uh um genetic
predisposition. What's happening is you
have testosterone it converts to diet
testosterone through the enzyme
falafroductase predominantly five alpha
reductase 2 and uh that DHT then can
bind to various tissues in the body um
you know obviously the most one of the
most the prostate being one of the you
know prominent ones that we know about
but certainly it binds to the hair
follicles and a lot of that process
happens as a um you know as an intric
process And uh when that DHT binds
there, it basically um will cause
shortening of the antigen phase. It'll
lead to hair thinning, miniaturization
the hair over time, but over these
repeat cycles the hair falls out. And
it's a bit of a spectrum because a lot
of men will have very small levels of
susceptibility. A lot of men will have
um very major levels of susceptibility
to that DHT.
And as this uh process happens um
for someone who introduces testosterone
more testosterone in the body with
testosterone replacement therapy you're
getting a little bit of upregulation in
that DHT process just because you're
feeding some more substrate into that
process. And so um what's very important
to know is that when someone post takes
TRT you're not causing the hair loss. If
someone has pre-existing predisposition
to hair loss, then that process can get
a little bit accelerated. So, that's the
key thing that I like to really point
out because you want to make sure a
patient comes in, they take TRT, they're
not thinking, well, now I'm going to
lose all my hair. I mean, you know, we
have to make sure we are very clear on
that. And I think um [clears throat]
more and more patients seem to
understand that nowadays, but you're
accelerating a process that's already
going to be happening to begin with. And
um it is a major like spectrum too
because a lot of men will have very
limited amounts of hair loss. Some men
will have very significant amounts of
hair loss at age 19 20. Some guys when
they're like 58 they might start
noticing more and more thinning thing
and so it's a wide spectrum and a lot of
that has to do with the differences in
the five alpha reductes a lot of the
different genes that affect um
prostaglandins and localized
inflammation in the scalp. There's
multiple things that play a role. And
then I think when we get into the
treatment options um because I think
that's where you start to get into some
controversy on certain medications. So
uh for me I like to list out all the
different uh options that are available.
So I mean topical minoxidal is um you
know one of the most main stays of
treatment um you know here in Canada,
United States. It's just over the
counter. You can just go pick it up from
your pharmacy, apply it. Um I'm not sure
if that's the case in Europe, but it's a
it's over the counter, but um
and that's usually a mainstay treatment.
You're not really targeting that whole
five uh five alpha reductase DHT
um mechanism. You're more so through
five or six different mechanisms
stimulating more and more hair growth.
And so topical minoxidil actually
becomes a bit of a treatment option for
other types of hair loss as well like
telogen and fluvium and other kinds of
hair loss rather than just solely for
male pattern baldness. I mean women can
also routinely use it. Um side point it
is toxic to some pets. So I think a bit
of a um bit of FYI for some people who
use it.
Then on the same minoxidal side um you
know it doesn't work that well for some
people and one reason we run into that
is some men have or I shouldn't say some
men some humans in general have a um a
deficiency in the enzyme uh salt 101 and
so minoxidil as a drug when it's applied
it's actually a prod drug it has to
convert to the active form through the
enzyme salt one sulfur transferase and
So some men have or sorry some people
have a deficiency in that enzyme. And so
um what we can do is we can apply a
medication like adapylene to the scalp
as an adjunct with the minoxidil to help
upregulate that conversion of the
minoxidil to its active form. Um and
then uh it the applane also because it
helps increase skin cell turnover. It
also incre increases penetration of that
minoxul into the deep into the scalp. So
um it helps improve the um absorption
close to on par with like the oral
minoxidil and oral minoxidal another
option too. Old blood pressure
medication um a lot of the people here
some people dermatologists still will
prescribe for hair loss. Um I will
occasionally prescribe it for some
patients depending on what options are
available. Um it does have um you know
in the United States the FDA they put a
blackbox warning for like spontaneous
paricardial fusion. So it's a risk um
you know it's one of an informed risk
benefit discussion with the patient. Um
I will sometimes use it for other kinds
of hair loss as well. Um but it's a risk
calculation I think like anything else.
And then uh more famously I think
obvious or infamously finasteride um you
know approved in many countries for
treatment of androgenic alipcia usually
use that 1 milligram daily dosing and uh
with you're shutting off that five alpha
reductase pathway well shouldn't say
shutting down you're doing a reduction
by about 70% and so you're getting
decreased DHT at the scalp
um you're getting efficacy in terms of
uh um improving the hair loss. And then
there's the trade-off risk where you
carry a background risk of you know um
sexual dysfunction, erectile
dysfunction, libido, mood changes and so
on. And then uh with the caveat that a
subset of those people when they
discontinue the finasteride might not
have recovery of that um of those of
those you know uh you know physiologic
processes like normal sexual function.
And so this is one of those cases where
you ultimately uh you know my take on it
is you try uh look at the studies you
look at this where the patient
specifically and you look at the data I
would say [clears throat] data that's
more neutral objective and then you know
they can make an informed decision what
they want to do um dutasteride is
another option I don't prescribe that in
my practice generally for um hair loss
um just with the the systemic side
effect risk I mean I think It's quite uh
quite profound. Um
and then topical uh finasteride and
dutasteride are um options and the
topical finasteride should ideally have
about um I would say pretty minimal.
Again, this is one of those compounding
pharmacy things where it's like
you don't know for sure like how
reliable it is and went from one
pharmacy to the next to other guy to the
other town. It's there's gonna be
variability and so um but if you're
getting a good product I mean it should
be the p the absorption should be
adequate the systemic absorption should
be minimal that's I guess you could say
theoretically speaking that's how it
should be um a little bit pricier um but
it's an option um on the list on our
list of options topical dutasteride
um theoretically again this is just more
more consider more academic but
theoretically it's an option but um the
molecule size quite big and so I've been
I guess a little skeptical on how it's
getting against the scalp but um I do
recall seeing one piece of data that
showed there was absorption but again I
would say a little more academic perhaps
um dutasteride misotherapy so the
rationale being you're injecting
dutasteride about you know 3 to four
millimeters into the the scalp and
you're [snorts]
um getting very localized absorption
with minimal systemic absorption.
And the rationale why dutasteride is
used is um the long halflife
essentially. And so you're able to do
periodic injections every couple months
and lower that localized DHT
without getting systemic absorption of
DHT.
And uh I think when you move past I mean
you have your DHT blockade medications,
you have your minoxal blockade
medications, then you start moving into
some other class of cosmetic treatments
essentially PRP, PRF, right? Like
therapy and so on. Um so that's kind of
under the cosmetic umbrella. Of course,
you have your hair transplant option.
People will get hair transplant will
still need some maintenance therapy
afterwards. I think some people who
pursue hair transplant don't always know
that, but often need some maintenance
therapy after. And so I think for the
patient who starts on TRT, I think it's
really just they need to know if you
have a predisposition. That's a big if.
Then there could be an acceleration of
that process on TRT. Um and then it's
really just that they're aware of it.
Doesn't mean that we tell them, hey, you
need to care about this. It's just
personal choice. If they care about it,
they need to know that it can accelerate
that process. Doesn't actually mean
that'll happen. I mean, I do have some
patients who have a little bit of um
you know background androgenic alopecia
who go on TRT and they don't generally
get much worsening of their hair loss
and then uh from there it's really just
monitoring I mean if someone wants to
intervene on it then we can intervene
with them if they don't want to
intervene then we don't need to um and
then beyond that it just you know just
remains a a personal choice um you know
and then I get questions about
supplements I tell them well supplements
probably if you're taking some like
biotin or something it's not gonna
you know, you're not going to go from
major thinning to like complete reversal
of that. Um, there's other things like
ketoconol shampoo, localized anti-DHD
effects. Maybe it works as an adjunct, a
little add-on. I'm not sure it's like a
it's not going to completely reverse the
process. And then um and then obviously
making sure their diet, lifestyle,
everything's optimized, stressors, and
so on. I do see patients with mixed
taggenlovium and um androgenic alipcia.
It's like well they're very stressed and
they're losing hair from that and
simultaneously they're also pain. So got
to make sure we don't mix those two
things up.
>> What do you think about combining
minoxidil or topical finasteride with a
micro needling at home?
>> Yeah, I think uh definitely the
combination therapy I think can work
mechanistically can work quite well. Um
we actually have a lot of products here
that are um automatically like combined
therapy topical topical combined agents.
They can apply them twice a day because
a lot of the patients you'll tell them
um you know like apply this twice a day
apply this twice a day but then you get
to the reality of it. It's like the
person has a greasy scalp basically 24
hours a day. So um I think combined
therapy I think can work quite well with
minoxidil and the topical finasteride.
you avoid systemic absorption risk of
the finastride as well. Micro needling I
think has especially when combined with
other agents like that I think has some
reasonably good evidence behind it
efficacy. So I think it's a pretty good
option.
>> Mhm. Okay.
>> Yeah, that's clear. Um that's my
experience as well. I prescribe a lot of
minoxidil um very rarely finasteride
because I'm a bit afraid of the post
finasteride syndrome
reviews and witnesses that I had on the
channel already. So
>> yeah, I don't I don't take it too far. I
try to reason with them and uh explain
that it's just a normal process, not a
disease. And yeah, that it's just
genetically if you're prone to it, it
might accelerate a little bit and that's
all. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think they understand that
it's not like a a disease that they're
getting. I think that's the key part.
>> Yeah.
>> Um genetic predisposition, it's not a
cause either because I think
>> um some people get afraid that like oh
well I took TRT and that's why like this
is going to happen. It's the same thing
with the heart disease and the prostate
and everything, right? It's in that
whole same umbrella of like listen like
these are not the causes.
>> TRT is not the cause of these things.
Mhm.
>> And so yeah, if you have genetic
predisposition, then you have genetic
predisposition, right? And then
obviously making sure it's not a
completely different diagnosis either.
>> Yeah. Personally, I lost my hair way
before TRT. My grandfather lost his hair
without TRT whatsoever. So yeah, if
you're genetically prone to it, you
might as well accept it. And uh
>> yeah, but that's difficult for young
guys. If they come to me 22 years old,
25, and they're thinning. Yeah, it's
difficult to accept sometimes and we we
might try something to uh postpone the
the shedding.
>> Yeah.